A tsunami of questions flew out of the mouths of children who the world didn't think were interested. And they themselves had not known they cared. And as they wrote and debated, rather than seeing the films as artifacts, they began to see themselves. I have an aunt who is a wonderful storyteller. In a moment she can invoke images of running barefoot on Table Mountain and playing cops and robbers. Quite recently she told me that in 1948, two of her sisters and my father traveled on a boat to Israel without my grandparents. When the sailors mutinied at sea in a demand for humane conditions, it was these teenagers that fed the crew. I was past 40 when my father died. He never mentioned that journey. My mother's mother left Europe in a hurry without her husband, but with her three-year-old daughter and diamonds sewn into the hem of her skirt. After two years in hiding, my grandfather appeared in London. He was never right again. And his story was hushed as he assimilated. My story started in England with a clean slate and the silence of immigrant parents. I had "Anne Frank," "The Great Escape," "Shoah," "Triumph of the Will." It was Leni Riefenstahl in her elegant Nazi propaganda who gave context to what the family had to endure. These films held what was too hurtful to say out loud, and they became more useful to me than the whispers of survivors and the occasional glimpse of a tattoo on a maiden aunt's wrist. Purists may feel that fiction dissipates the quest of real human understanding, that film is too crude to tell a complex and detailed history, or that filmmakers always serve drama over truth. But within the reels lie purpose and meaning. As one 12-year-old said after watching "Wizard of Oz," "Every person should watch this, because unless you do you may not know that you too have a heart." We honor reading, why not honor watching with the same passion? Consider "Citizen Kane" as valuable as Jane Austen. Agree that "Boyz n the Hood," like Tennyson, offers an emotional landscape and a heightened understanding that work together. Each a piece of memorable art, each a brick in the wall of who we are. And it's okay if we remember Tom Hanks better than astronaut Jim Lovell or have Ben Kingsley's face superimposed onto that of Gandhi's. And though not real, Eve Harrington, Howard Beale, Mildred Pierce are an opportunity to discover what it is to be human, and no less helpful to understanding our life and times as Shakespeare is in illuminating the world of Elizabethan England. We guessed that film, whose stories are a meeting place of drama, music, literature and human experience, would engage and inspire the young people participating in FILMCLUB. What we could not have foreseen was the measurable improvements in behavior, confidence and academic achievement. Once-reluctant students now race to school, talk to their teachers, fight, not on the playground, but to choose next week's film -- young people who have found self-definition, ambition and an appetite for education and social engagement from the stories they have witnessed. Our members defy the binary description of how we so often describe our young. They are neither feral nor myopically self-absorbed. They are, like other young people, negotiating a world with infinite choice, but little culture of how to find meaningful experience. We appeared surprised at the behaviors of those who define themselves by the size of the tick on their shoes, yet acquisition has been the narrative we have offered. If we want different values we have to tell a different story, a story that understands that an individual narrative is an essential component of a person's identity, that a collective narrative is an essential component of a cultural identity, and without it it is impossible to imagine yourself as part of a group. Because when these people get home after a screening of "Rear Window" and raise their gaze to the building next door, they have the tools to wonder who, apart from them, is out there and what is their story. Thank you. (Applause)
Una oleada de preguntas salieron de las bocas de los chicos que el mundo pensaba que no estaban interesados. Y ellos mismos tampoco sabían que les importaba. Mientras escribían y discutían, en lugar de ver las películas como mera ficción, comenzaron a verse a ellos mismos. Tengo una tía que es excelente narradora de historias. En un momento, ella puede evocar imágenes de sus carreras descalza en la Montaña de la Mesa, jugando a policías y ladrones. Hace poco, ella me contó que en 1948, dos de sus hermanas y mi padre viajaron en barco a Israel sin mis abuelos. Cuando los marineros se amotinaron para solicitar condiciones dignas, fueron estas jovencitas quienes alimentaron a la tripulación. Cuando mi padre murió yo tenía más de 40 años. Él nunca mencionó ese viaje. La madre de mi madre salió de Europa de prisa, sin su esposo, pero con su hija de 3 años y diamantes cosidos en el ruedo de su falda. Luego de dos años de estar escondido, mi abuelo apareció en Londres. Nunca más volvió a estar bien. Y callaron su historia a medida que él se integraba. Mi historia comenzó en Inglaterra con un borrón y cuenta nueva y el silencio de padres inmigrantes. Tuve «Ana Frank», «El gran escape», «Shoah», «El triunfo de la voluntad». Fue Leni Riefenstahl con su elegante propaganda nazi quien dio contexto a lo que mi familia tuvo que soportar. Estas películas contenían lo que era muy doloroso de decir en voz alta y fueron más útiles para mí que los susurros de los sobrevivientes y el ocasional vistazo a un tatuaje en la muñeca de una tía soltera. Los puristas pueden pensar que la ficción disipa la búsqueda de un entendimiento realmente humano, que el cine es muy burdo como para relatar una historia compleja y detallada o que los directores de cine ponen siempre el drama por sobre la verdad. Pero en los carretes está el propósito y el significado. Como decía una niña de 12 años luego de ver «El mago de Oz», «Todas las personas deben ver esto, porque si no lo hacen puede que no sepan que también tienen corazón». Respetamos la lectura, ¿por qué no respetar también el cine con la misma pasión? Pensemos que el «Ciudadano Kane» es tan valioso como Jane Austen. Acordemos que «Los dueños de la calle» tanto como Tennyson, ofrecen un panorama emocional y un entendimiento intensificado que funcionan juntos. Cada pieza de arte de antología es un ladrillo en el muro de lo que somos. Y está bien si recordamos mejor a Tom Hanks que al astronauta Jim Lovell o tenemos la imagen de Ben Kingsley superpuesta a la de Gandhi. Y Eve Harrington, Howard Beale, Mildred Pierce, aunque no son reales, nos ofrecen la oportunidad de descubrir lo que significa ser humano y no es menos útil que comprender nuestra vida y nuestro tiempo como Shakespeare al iluminar el mundo de la Inglaterra isabelina. Supusimos que el cine cuyas historias son un punto de reunión del drama, la música, la literatura y la experiencia humana, acogerían e inspirarían a los jóvenes a que participaran en FILMCLUB. Lo que no nos imaginábamos eran las notables mejoras en el comportamiento, confianza y logros académicos. Los estudiantes, reacios de antes, ahora corren a la escuela, hablan con sus profesores, pelean, no en el patio de la escuela, sino para elegir la próxima película de la semana, jóvenes que se han autodefinido, tienen ambición y apetito por una educación y un compromiso social, a partir de las historias de las que han sido testigos. Nuestros participantes desafían la descripción binaria de cómo describimos con frecuencia a nuestros jóvenes. No son salvajes ni están ensimismados de manera miope. Son como otra gente joven que negocia en un mundo con infinidad de opciones, pero con poca cultura para encontrar una experiencia significativa. Nos sorprendemos de los comportamientos de aquellos que se definen a sí mismos por las cosas que tienen, aunque hemos ofrecido la narrativa como conocimiento. Si queremos valores diferentes, tenemos que contar otra historia, una historia que entienda que la narrativa de un individuo es un componente esencial de la identidad de una persona, que una narrativa colectiva, es un componente esencial de una identidad cultural, y que sin esta, es imposible imaginarse uno mismo como parte de un grupo. Porque cuando estas personas regresan a casa después de ver «La ventana indiscreta» y levantan la mirada al edificio de al lado, tienen las herramientas para adivinar quiénes, aparte de ellos, están ahí afuera y cuál es su historia. Gracias. (Aplausos)